José Emilio Pacheco Papers, circa 1940s-2010s: Finding Aid C1619
Manuscripts Division
- Writings, 1940-2010s; 22 boxes
  - Writings by others, 1946 May-2008; 1 box
    - "O repouso do fogo," tradução de Floriano Martins, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 9a)
    - Opiniones acerca de "El principio del placer", undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 10)
      Includes opinions by Sergio Vázquez Piñón, Alonso Nikolai Melena Ruíz, Miguel Angel Soto, Juana Quiñones Serrano, and others.
    - Prólogo a José Emilio Pacheco, "Antología poética," Hernán Sánchez Mtz. de Pinillos, circa 2002; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 11)
    - Prólogo de Luis García Montero a los, "Cuatro cuartetos," traducido por José Emilio Pacheco, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 12)
    - "Salvador Díaz Mirón: malignidad y melancolía," Willebaldo Herrera, 1999 May; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 13)
    - "Silence of the Moon: Theme and Variations," translated by James Nolan, 1999; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 14)
    - "Sobriedad," Juan Luis Pla Benito, 1982-1983; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 14a)
    - "The Amusement Park," translated by Katherine Silver, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 15)
    - "The Circus at Night," translated by Cynthia Steele, circa 1994; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 16)
    - "The Exuberant Years: Mexican-American Literary and Cultural Relations Between the Two Wars," John L. Brown, circa 1984; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 17)
    - "The Silence of the Moon" translation, circa 1996; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 18)
    - "The Spider of the Holiday House Motel," translated by Luis Rebaza-Soraluz and Michael Collier, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 1 folder (Box B-001290, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1940-2010s; 10 boxes
  This file group consists of correspondence from various colleagues, publishers, family, and friends. Frequent and notable names found throughout the correspondence include Octavio Paz, Juan Vicente Melo, Carlos Fuentes, José Miguel Oviedo, Sergio Galindo, Félix Grande, Guillermo Cabrera Infante, Homero Aridjis, Carlos Monsivaís, Rosario Castellanos, José Bianco, Vicente Rojo, Hugo J. Verani (University of California, Davis), Saúl Sosnowski (University of Maryland at College Park), Juan Armando Epple (University of Oregon), Bruno Arcudi (State University of New York at Buffalo), Manuel Andújar (Alianza Editorial), Mario Muchnik (Muchnik Editores and Ariel/Seix Barral Editoriales), Fernando Vidal Buzzi (Editorial Sudamericana), and many others. Given the disorganized state of the material upon receipt in the repository, the correspondence has been arranged chronologically (by decades), and only the correspondence that arrived in groupings or was easily identified has been separated, including that of Octavio Paz, Juan Vicente Melo, Carlos Fuentes, José Miguel Oviedo, Sergio Galindo, Bruno Arcudi, and the family correspondence, chiefly Pacheco´s wife, daughters, and mother.
  Additional description of names identified throughtout the correspondence was provided by PU gradudate student, Miguel Domínguez.
  - Correspondence, 1940s; 1 folder (Box B-001291, Folder 1)
    Cartas de: Ramón Pous Roca, Eduardo J. Lavalle Urbina, Evelio Berny Abreu.
  - Correspondence, circa 1950s; 1 folder (Box B-001291, Folder 2)
    Cartas de: Jaime García Terrés, Sofía Berny, Óscar Rodríguez, José de la Colina, Emilio Carballido, Alberto Trueba Urbina, César Humberto Isassi, Nuria Parés, Alfonso Reyes, Carlos R. Menendez, Perfecto Baranda Berrón, Manuel Lavalle Barret, Nazario Víctor Montejo Godoy, John H. Grepe, Antonio de Undurraga, Manuel Scorza, Roberto Blanco Moheno, Elías Nandino, Juan Vicente Melo.
    Cartas a: Juan José Arreola y Carlos Fuentes.
  - Correspondence, circa 1960s; 5 folders (Box B-001291, Folder 3-7)
    Carpeta 3 - Cartas de: Juan Manuel Torres, Eduardo Kissam, Aníbal Ford, Andrés Huerta, Juan José Hernández, Perfecto Baranda Berrón, Joaquim de Montezuma de Carvalho, Dionicio Morales, Cecilia Martínez Lamarque René Marqués, Alfonso Mejía, Fernando Vidal Buzzi, Luis Suardíaz, Alfonso Garza, Marco Antonio Montes de Oca, Juan Antonio Ayala, Lazlo Moussong, Winston Orrillo, Vicente Aleixandre, Guillermo Cabrera Infante, Haydeé Santamaría, L. Greenwood, Donald Davie, Alberto Díaz-Lastra, Frank Dauster, Salvador Barros Sierra, Alcira Soust Scaffo, Gordon Brotherston, Luciano Russi, José Luis Cano, Monserrat Sabater, Blanca Varela, Federico Campbell, Ernesto Sabato, Marta Mosquera, Gordon R. Silver, Eduardo Desnoes, Julio Jaime Julia, R. A. Platt, Francisco Ayala, Alfonso Grosso, Salvador Novo, José Vázquez Amaral, Ángel Flores, Alfredo Roggiano, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Félix Grande, Stella de Suescún, Richard Reeve, Ernesto de la Torre Villar, Juan Gustavo Cobo Borda, Gonzalo Martré, Rebeca Lozada, Rafael Castillo, José Miguel Oviedo, Esquivel Navarrete, Magda Graniela Rodríguez, Alfonso Reyes.
    Cartas a: José E. Mindlin, Rodolfo Usigli, Juan Rejano, Homero Aridjis, Víctor Sandoval, Tom Raworth, Manuel Andújar, W. R. Dell, Lewis Rubman.
    Carpeta 4 - Cartas de: Sergio Pitol, Antón Arrufat, Héctor Azar, José Antonio Alcaraz, Homero Aridjis, Juan García Ponce, Stuart M. Gross, Juan Goytisolo, Claude Couffon, Henrique González Casanova, Gastón García Cantú, Rafael Giménez Siles, Sergio Galindo, César Rodríguez Chicharro, Ricardo Garibay, Ángel Rama, Manuel Tuñón de Lara, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Haydée Santamaría, José Luis González, Carlos Fuentes, Ferndo González Gortázar, Luis Suardíaz, Jean Michel Fossey, Álvaro Menen Desleal, Héctor Álvarez Murena, Jean Franco, Laura Emilia Pacheco, Jaime Torres Bodet, Miguel Ángel Asturias, Tom Raworth, Armando Álvarez Bravo, Eduardo Desnoes, Julio Cortázar, Julieta Campos, Emilio Carballido, Blanca Varela, José Donoso, Orlando Alomá, Fernando Benítez, Wilberto Cantón, Luis Cernuda, José Miguel Oviedo, Juan Gustavo Cobo Borda, Boyd G. Carter, Alberto Díaz-Lastra, J. M. Cohen, Miguel Barnet, Rodolfo Usigli, Edmundo Aray, Antonio de Undurraga, José Vázquez Amaral, José María Alfonso, Efraín Huerta, Sebastián Salazar Bondy, Winston Orrillo, Ramón Xirau, José-Miguel Ullán, Alfredo Palacios Espinosa, Félix Grande, Pedro Lastra, William Peden, Arnaldo Orfila, Francisco Blanco, Fernando Charry Lara, Víctor Seix, Ana Castellar, Sergio Mondragón, Gustavo García Saraví, Manuel Andújar, Julio Ortega, José E. Mindlin, Juan José Hernández, Patrick Geagh, Héctor Manjarrez, Felipe García Beraza, Roque Dalton, Liliana Porter, José Carlos Becerra, Octavio Paz.
    Cartas a: George O. Schanzer y Ernesto Cardenal.
    Carpeta 5 - Cartas de: Miguel Barnet, Enrique Lihn, Jaime Posada, Alberto Díaz-Lastra, Ms. L. Greenwood, Héctor Manjarrez, Haydee Santamaría, Homero Aridjis, Maurice English, Federico Campbell, Vicente Aleixandre, Armando Ayala Anguiano, Fernando Vidal Buzzi, Miguel Álvarez G., Margaret Randall, J. M. Cohen, Roberto Díaz García, Mike Gonzales, Marco Antonio Montes de Oca, Himilce Novas, Ricardo Balderas, Aníbal Ford, Alfonso Manuel Castañeda, Raúl Cáceres Carenzo, José de la Colina, Salvador Barros Sierra, René Marqués, Tom Raworth, Juan Goytisolo, Livio Gómez, José Miguel Oviedo, José Bianco, Fernando Charry Lara, José Donoso, Vincent R. Tortora, Gordon Brotherston, A. E. Sloman, R. A. Platt, George Hyde, Donald Davie, M. Elliott, E. Newcomb, Rowland Jones, Winston Orrillo, Gastón García Cantú, José-Miguel Ullán, Rodolfo Usigli, Carlos Fuentes, Frank Dauster, Emilio Carballido, Miguel Covarrubias, Claude Couffon, Armando Álvarez Bravo, Fernando Benítez, Carlos Barral.
    Cartas a: José Miguel Oviedo, C. M. Stanford.
    Carpeta 6 - Cartas de: Miguel Barnet, Enrique Lihn, Jaime Posada, Alberto Díaz-Lastra, Ms. L. Greenwood, Héctor Manjarrez, Haydee Santamaría, Homero Aridjis, Maurice English, Federico Campbell, Vicente Aleixandre, Armando Ayala Anguiano, Fernando Vidal Buzzi, Miguel Álvarez G., Margaret Randall, J. M. Cohen, Roberto Díaz García, Mike Gonzales, Marco Antonio Montes de Oca, Himilce Novas, Ricardo Balderas, Aníbal Ford, Alfonso Manuel Castañeda, Raúl Cáceres Carenzo, José de la Colina, Salvador Barros Sierra, René Marqués, Tom Raworth, Juan Goytisolo, Livio Gómez, José Miguel Oviedo, José Bianco, Fernando Charry Lara, José Donoso, Vincent R. Tortora, Gordon Brotherston, A. E. Sloman, R. A. Platt, George Hyde, Donald Davie, M. Elliott, E. Newcomb, Rowland Jones, Winston Orrillo, Gastón García Cantú, José-Miguel Ullán, Rodolfo Usigli, Carlos Fuentes, Frank Dauster, Emilio Carballido, Miguel Covarrubias, Claude Couffon, Armando Álvarez Bravo, Fernando Benítez, Carlos Barral.
    Carpeta 7 - Cartas de: Sergio Pitol, Mike Gonzales, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Elvio Romero, Manuel Andújar, Margaret Randall, Alberto Díaz-Lastra, Tom Raworth, Val Raworth, Jean Franco, José-Miguel Ullán, Dorothy E. Tanck, Laura Emilia Pacheco, Miguel Donoso Pareja, John Martin, Livio Gómez, Hugo Gutiérrez Vega, Miguel Barnet, Blanca Varela, Ruth Malther, José Ángel Valente, Gordon Brotherston, Pedro Lastra, Porfirio Martínez Peñaloza, Segundo Guevara D., Federico Campbell, Juan Goytisolo, Alejo Carpentier, Rodolfo Usigli, Frederic Will, Roberto Dávila, Homero Aridjis, Jean Michel Fossey, István Dely, Sebastián Salazar Bondy, Arnaldo Orfila, Miguel Salas Anzures, Manuel Durán, Héctor Álvarez Murena, Ángel Rama, Paul Westheim, Agustín Yáñez, Ramón Xirau, José Donoso, Guillermo García Oropeza, Salvador Barros Sierra, Fernando Vidal Buzzi.
    Cartas a: Luis Cernuda, Carlos Monsiváis, Julio Ortega, Henrique González Casanova, Rodolfo Usigli, James F. Mathias.
  - Correspondence, circa 1960s; 1 folder (Box B-001292, Folder 1)
    Cartas de: Carlos Monsiváis, Salvador Novo, José-Miguel Ullán, Rosa María Hernández Brito, Tom Raworth, Manuel Andújar, Noe Jitrik, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Alberto Díaz-Lastra, Nicolás Guillén, Henrique González Casanova, Leopoldo Ayala, Ida Vitale, Antonio de Undurraga, Ramón Xirau, Antón Arrufat, Armando Álvarez Bravo, Salvador Azuela, Miguel Álvarez Acosta, David Alfaro Siqueiros, Francisco Ayala, Max Aub, Homero Aridjis, Rafael Giménez Siles, David N. Arce, Rubén Anaya Sarmiento, José Agustín, Aníbal Ford, Margarita Galetar, Miguel González Avelar, Guillermo García Oropeza, Miguel Ángel Fernández, Dionys Mascolo, José E. Mindlin, Héctor Manjarrez, Juan Manuel Torres, Manuel Arenas Zambrano, Marcia Leiseca, Ángel Flores, Jaime Salinas Bonmatí, Octavio Rivera Farber y Augusto Vasconcelos Ortiz, Víctor M. Pavón Abreu, Hugo Gutiérrez Vega, Antonio Gálvez, Rodorfo Usigli, Félix Grande, George Hyde, William Peden, John Martin, Julio Ortega, Gordon Brotherston, Pierre Jean Oswald, Dorothy E. Tanck, Margaret Sansom, Juan García Ponce, Fernando Vidal Buzzi Giovanni Quessep, María Pilar Donoso, Alicia y Francisco Zendejas, José Luis Martínez.
    Cartas a: A Whitney Ellsworth, Blanca Varela, Mike Gonzales, Juan Goytisolo, Frederic Will, José Angel Valente, Pedro Lastra, Gustavo Esteva, Fernando González Gortázar, Enrique Pezzoni, José Miguel Oviedo, Alfredo Roggiano, Miguel Barnet, Julio Scherer García, Samuel Rovinski.
  - Correspondence, circa 1970s; 4 folders (Box B-001292, Folder 2-5)
    Carpeta 2 - Cartas de: Lowell Dunham, Ivar Ivask, Rodolfo Usigli, Federico Campbell, Gordon Brotherston, Plinio Apuleyo Mendoza, Hugo Gutiérrez Vega, Homero Aridjis, Marvin D'Lugo, Alfredo A. Roggiano, Félix Grande, Lewis H. Rubman, Jean Michel Fossey, Antonio Gálvez, Elena Soriano, Dámaso Murúa, Marian Coope, Mike Gonzales, Ángel Flores, Fernando Ferreira de Loanda, Nicolás Suescún, Luis Alfonso Diez, Fernando Curiel, Julio Ortega, Gerardo Ciper, Roberto Dávila Gómez Palacio y Ma. Teresa Cabrera de Dávila, Francisco Pabón, Juan Goytisolo, Pedro Lastra, Tom Raworth, Thomas Hoeksema, Ricardo Gullón, Allen W. Phillips, Carlos Ortiz Gil, Rosario Castellanos, Nicholas Catanoy, Carlos Monsiváis, José Luis Merino, Manuel Bravo, Leandro Garza Reyes, Liliana Porter, Jaime Goded, Dean H Schoelkopf, Fernando Benítez, Mario Muchnik, Mariano Flores Castro, Stefan Baciu, José Antonio Maravall, Norman Mangouni, Guillermo Schavelzon, Juan Gustavo Cobo Borda, Enrique Fierro, Joaquim de Montezuma de Carvalho, Víctor M. Pavón Abreu, Vicente Rojo, Fernando del Paso, Celso y Betty Lafer, Elías Nandino, John Martin, George Mc Whirter, Jean Franco.
    Cartas a: Rodolfo Usigli, Amadou Seydou, Manuel Durán, Harold Livermore, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Haroldo de Campos, Sergio Pitol, Jesús Silva Herzog, Mario Vargas Llosa, Enrique Caracciolo-Trejo, Bertalicia Peralta.
    Carpeta 3 - Cartas de: Ángel Flores, Allen W. Philllips, Stefan Baciu, Stella Alonzo, Federico Campbell, Edmundo Valadez, Tom Raworth, Alfredo Roggiano, Enrique Caracciolo-Trejo, Jorge M. Pérez Ponce, Rodolfo Usigli, Juan Goytisolo, Oscar Rodríguez, Fernando Ferreira de Loanda, Ann Bree, Manuel Andújar, Thomas Hoeksema, Roberto Dávila (Gómez Palacio), Julio Ortega, Clifford Smith, José Vázquez Amaral, Antonio Gálvez, Gabriel Vargas Sánchez, Giovanni Quessep, Frederic Will, Carlos Monsiváis, Homero Aridjis, Nicolás Suescún, Fernando de Tola Habich, Juan Gustavo Cobo Borda, Jean Franco, Tino Villanueva, Aníbal Ford, Samuel Rovinski, Víctor M. Sandoval, Hugo Gutiérrez Vega, Darío Cantón, Ángel Rama, Ricardo Castillo, Jean Michel Fosey, Ana Castellar, Jaume J. Aymá Aubeyzon, Alberto Díaz Lastra, José Luis Merino, José E. Pérez, Haroldo de Campos, Éva Tóth, Bob. D. Lewis, Ronald Christ, Mariano Flores Castro, James F. Mathias, Mario Muchnick, Juan Jesús Armas Marcelo, Julio César Schara, Francisco Ayala, Concepción Silva Belinzon, Alicia Betsy Edwards, Félix Grande, Rafael Pineda, Gordon Brotherston, Manuel Mantero, Lewis H. Rubman, Pierre Zekeli, Patricia Llosa Urquidi, Joseph Sommers, Justo Arroyo, Francisco Sánchez-Castañer, Saúl Sosnowski, Guillermo Colussi, Eduardo Gudiño Kieffer, José Oliveira Bugallo, Joaquín Antonio Peñalosa, Marío Santiago Papasquiaro.
    Cartas a: Mario Vargas Llosa, entre otros autores no identificados.
    Carpeta 4 - Cartas de: Carlos Fuentes, Carlos Monsiváis, Enrique Caracciolo-Trejo, Gaby Brimmer, Francisco Ayala, Rosario Santos, Gregory Kolovakos, Ricardo D. Aguilar, Rodolfo Usigli, Gabriel Zaid, Julio Ortega, Rosario Castellanos, Manuel Puig, Carlos y Sonia Próspero, Donna Gerstenberger, José Donoso, Alicia Betsy Edwards, Marco Antonio Aguilar Cortés, Carlos Becerra Lacroix, Magdalena Oliver, José María Valverde, Stefan Baciu, Manuel Andújar, Juan Gustavo Cobo Borda, Mariano Flores Castro, José-Miguel Ullán, José M. Oxholm, Celso y Betty Lafer, Giovanni Quessep, Lewis H. Rubman, Tom Raworth, Héctor Hernández Schauer, Rafael Pineda, Abelardo Oquendo, Ida Vitale, Ángel Flores, Beatriz de Moura, Manuel Capetillo, Ángel Rama, Agustín Yáñez, Homero Aridjis, Luis Alfonso Diez, Guillermo García Oropeza, José Roberto Cea, Jorge M. Pérez Ponce, Thomas Hoeksema, Pierre Zekeli, Bárbara Litwin, Jean Franco, Armando Correia Pacheco, Samuel Rovinski.
    Cartas a: Agustín Yáñez, Aristeo Brito, Isabel Fraire, Lilvia Soto, Wayne Conner, entre otros autores no identificados.
    Carpeta 5 - Cartas de: Vicente Rojo, Julio Ortega, Claude Fell, David Hernández, Joseph Sommers, Juan Morales, J. Jesús Ramírez Gámez, Luis Leal, Haroldo de Campos, Jorge M. Pérez Ponce, Ofelia Cervántez de Martínez, Fernando Ferreira de Loanda, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Roque Dalton, Harold Livermore, Cristina Pacheco, Carlos Monsiváis, José Roberto Cea, I. Hansen, Tom Raworth, D. Pérez Franco, Sergio Gómez Montero, Luis Alfonso Diez, María del Carmen Berny de Pacheco y Laura Emilia Pacheco, Manuel Durán, Homero Aridjis, Juan Goytisolo, Samuel Rovinski, Federico Campbell, Juan Gustavo Cobo Borda, Manuel Manten, Mario Rivero, Joaquín Antonio Peñalosa, Agnes Gullón, Elena Castedo, Mario Muñoz, Allen W Phillips, José Juan Arrom, Gordon Brotherston, Alfonso González, Leonor Andrade, Antonio Carreño, John C. Broderick, Nancy Brunson, James F. Mathias, Mary E. Woodring, Claude Bernard, Norma Klahn, William F. Bernhardt, Hero Rodríguez Toro, Antonio Inclán Chávez, Juan Grijalbo, Guillermo Castro Ulloa, Amos Segala, Rafael Catalá, Ángel Rama, Thomas Hoeksema, Salvador García, Elaine West, Robert D. Cotrell, Leon I. Twarog, Albert Motos (Mario Muchnik), Eduardo Mejía, Magdalena García Pinto, Anne Fremantle, Ulalume González de León, Mark B. Lewis, Sonia Lombardo de Ruiz, Elena Soriano.
    Cartas a: José-Miguel Ullán, Stephen Schlesinger (Guggenheim Foundation), Fernando Ferreira de Loanda, Elsa Cross, Félix Grande, Julio Escoto, Carlos Francisco Echeverría, Rosario Santos, Robert. D. Cottrell, Noel Hancock, Juan Jesús Armas Marcelo.
  - Correspondence, circa 1970s; 5 folders (Box B-001293, Folder 1-5)
    Carpeta 1 - Cartas de: Ann Livermore, Bárbara Litwin, Stella Alonzo, Haroldo de Campos, Homero Aridjis, Betty Jane Nelson, Marian Skedgell, Pedro Lastra, María Pilar Donoso, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Jean Michel Fossey, Héctor Manjarrez, Hugo Gutiérrez Vega, Héctor Anaya, Salvador Novo, Federico Campbell, Luis Alfonso Diez, Tino Villanueva, Marco Nobel Villegas, Rodolfo Usigli, Joseph Sommers, Claude Fell, Mario Vargas LLosa, I. Hansen, Mariano Flores Castro, Octavio Armand, Georgette M. Don, Enrique Florescano, Celso Lafer, Julio Ortega, Stefan Baciu, Francisco Pabón, Mario Muchnick, Luis Vicens, Mike Gonzales, César A. Ramos, Leandro Garza-Reyes, Alfredo Roggiano, Ivan A. Schulman, Alfonso González, George Schanzer, James F. Mathias, Alfonso Contreras Muñiz, José López Portillo, Aurelio García Cantalapiedra, José Antonio Alcaraz, Manuel Mantero, Pedro F. de Andrea, Lilia D. Strout, Reynaldo Jiménez, Ida Vitale y Enrique Fierro, Eliana Rivero, Thomas Hoeksema, Mario Valdés, Lewis H. Rubman, Fernando Sánchez Sorondo, Francisco Rivera, Enrique Pupo-Walker y José J. Arrom, Fernando Ferreira de Loanda, María Aurora C. de Schmidt, Guillermo Sucre, Olga Connor, Kosrof Chantikian, Ángel Rama, Nacho, Salomón Laiter, Ivar Ivask, Antonio Alonso, Darío Cantón, Roberto Yahni.
    Cartas a: Ítalo López Vallecillos, Edmundo Valadés, José Miguel Oviedo, Carlos Ortiz Gil, Alex Verstringe, Enrique Verástegui, Ulalume González de León.
    Carpeta 2 - Cartas de: Vivian Nolan, Linda Scheer, Guillermo Sucre, Diana Berrondo de Hierro, Gabriel Navarrete, Fernando Ferreira de Loanda, Mario Rivero, Gordon Brotherston, Enrique Caracciolo-Trejo, Manuel Durán, Kirsten F. Nigro, Luis Leal, Martha Paley Francescato, Ronald Christ, José Donoso, Gordon N. Ray, Stephen L. Schlesinger, James F. Mathias, Tino Villanueva, José Antonio Peñalosa, John P. Dwyer, Emir Rodríguez Monegal, Félix Grande, George Schanzer, Dario Cantón, Aristeo Brito, Jorge M. Pérez Ponce, Felipe Orlando, Stefan Baciu, Alicia Betsy Edwards, Giovanni Quessep, Adrian Shubert, Cristina Peri Rossi, Mario Muchnik, Manuel Mantero, Luis Fernando Lara, Florentino López Lira, Carmen Balcells, Hugo Gutiérrez Vega, Jesús Silva Herzog, Víctor M. Sandoval, Mario J. Valdés, Ivan A. Schulman, Willaim J. Straub, José Luis Martínez, Enrique Florescano, Tom Raworth, Ivar Ivask, Henrique González Casanova, Arnaldo Orfila, Russel M. Cluff, Thomas Hoeksema, Lowell Dunham, Darío Jaramillo Agudelo, Margarito Cuéllar, Jaime Turrent, Bárbara Litwin, Petch Peden, Marcelo Uribe, Saúl Sosnowski, Ángel Rama, Antonio Alonso Jiménez.
    Cartas a: Eduardo Gudiño Kieffer, Concepción Silva Bélinzon, Alastair Reid, Mariano Flores Castro, José Olivio Jiménez, Dionisio Cañas y Alejandro Oliveros
    Carpeta 3 - Cartas de: Enrique Florescano, Alejandro Oliveros, Ángel Rama, José Manuel Giménez, Beth Miller, Martha Paley Francescato, León Davidoff, José María Valverde, Olga Connor, Rafael Caldera, Lewis H. Rubman, Alicia Reyes, Manuel Mantero, James F. Mathias, Stephen Schlesinger, James W. Wilkie, José Donoso, Alberto J. Carlos, Mario Muchnik, Alfredo Castañeda, Alicia Betsy Edwards, Ignacio Rodríguez, Raúl Cáceres Carenzo, Serafina Ramírez, Julio Ortega, Carlos Cortínez, René de Costa, Dorothy Brickman, Leon I. Twarog, Gustavo Pérez Delgado, Juan Liscano, Mariano Flores Castro, Hugo Gutiérrez Vega.
    Cartas a: Mario Vargas LLosa, Juan Marsé, Juan Pedro Quiñonero, Tom Raworth, William J. Straubb, Frederick Luciani.
    Carpeta 4 - Cartas de: Ernesto Trejo, Luis Dávila, Eduard L. Piña, René de Costa, James F. Mathias, Stephen Schlesinger, Rosaura Romero Ramírez, Luis García Morales, Ronald Christ, Gregory Kolovakos, Arturo Guzmán, Thomas Hoeksema, Peter G. Earle, Ivan Schulman, Sonia Lombardo de Ruiz, Alastair Reid, Martín Luis Guzmán Ferrer, Andrew Debicki, Saúl Sosnowski, Margaret Jacobson, Antonio Carreño, Olga Connor, John C. Broderick, Georgette M. Dorn, George McWhirter, Julio Ortega, Carlos Cortínez, Óscar Oliva Ruiz, Félix Grande y José Antonio Maravall, John F. Garganigo, Roberto Cantú, Marta Lynch, José L. Llovera B., Lewis H. Rubman, Leonor Andrade, Elsa Cross, Linda Scheer, Alejandro Oliveros, Octavio Armand, Mario Muchik, Mariano Flores Castro, Elena Castedo, Ángel Rama, Francisco Rivera, Mario Vargas LLosa, Mario J. Valdés, Sergio Ramírez, Reynaldo Jiménez, Francisco Hernández, Jaime García Terrés, Luis López Álvarez, Guillermo García Oropeza.
    Cartas a: Benito Milla, Darío Jaramillo Agudelo, Arnaldo Orfila, Mario Rivero, Graciela N. Jantz, Fernando Galiana, Antonio de Undurraga, Julio Escoto, Lizandro Chávez Alfaro, Rodolfo Cardona, Guillermo Sucre, Yeyette Bostelman, Juan Gustavo Cobo Borda, Madame Bernard-Coursodon, André Gregory.
    Carpeta 5 - Cartas de: Ronald Christ, Alaistair Reid, Alexander Coleman, Frederick Luciani, José María Guelbenzu, Rosa Aguilar, Elías Nandino, Luis B. Eyzaguirre Mary Gill, Joel Hancock, Octavio Armand, John L. Brown, Maureen Ahern, José Luis Giménez-Frontin, Carlos Cortínez, Joseph John Jova, Alicia Betsy Edwards, Dionisio Cañas, Félix Grande, Russell M. Cluff, Jesse T. Reinburg, Gustavo Pérez, Georgette M. Dorn, José A. Friedl Zapata, Saúl Sosnowski, Warren E. Preece, José Luis Cano, Arnaldo Orfila, Dieter Saalman, Rēgas Kappatos, Fernando J. Lentini, Saúl Pabello Rojas, Jesús Silva Herzog, José Lezama Lima, Manuel Mantero.
    Cartas a: Roque Dalton, Warren T. McReady, Allen W. Philips, Guillermo Sucre, René Costa.
  - Correspondence, circa 1980s; 5 folders (Box B-001294, Folder 1-5)
    Carpeta 1 - Cartas de: Rodolfo Echeverría Álvarez, Marcelo Uribe, Diego Luis Ortiz Sanclemente, Enrique Florescano, Martha Robles, Jeanne Maigne, Donia Mattalia Alonso, Ricardo Pau-Llosa, Aziza Bennani, Enrique Pupo-Walker, Russell M. Cluff, Ramón Layera, Rafael Rodríguez Castañeda, Vilma Fuentes, Cynthia Steele, Allen W. Phillips, Gustavo Jaramillo Giraldo, Julio Figueroa, Saúl Sosnowski, Julio Ortega, Jorge Alberto Lamoyi, Luis H. Peña, Mario J. Valdés, Thomas Hoeksema, Mario Muchnik, Alejandro Aldama, Seymour Menton, Angelina Muñiz-Huberman, Hugo J. Verani, Javier Pradera, René Solís, Jesús Morales Bermúdez, Pedro Fossas Requena, Rubén Castillo, Klaus Meyer-Minnemann, Ángel Flores, José Durand, Edgar O'Hara, John L. Brown, Carlos A. Solé, Carlos Ruvalcaba D., Neus Espresate, Guillermo Schidhuber de la Mora, Salomé Hernández, Jeannie Downey-Vanover, Tomás Borge, Jesús Quintero Mena, Hansi Durlach, Rita Gnutzmann, Robert Griffith, Kurt Neumann, Michi Strausfeld, César Humberto Isassi, Ana María Hernández de López, Juan Armando Epple, Pablo Luis Avila, José María Guelbenzu, Luis Miguel Aguilar Camín, Ignacio Betancourt, Verónica Cortínez, Lucy Fabiola Tello, Luis Camnitzer, Juana Rosa Pita, Tino Villanueva, Gilberto Castellanos.
    Cartas a: Otto Granados Roldán, Roberto Fernández Retamar, Mario Vargas LLosa.